<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse between monarchical and aristocratical government. Or a sober perswasive of all true-hearted Englishmen, to a willing conjunction with the Parliament of England in setting up the government of a common-wealth. By a true Englishman, and well-wisher to the good of this nation.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E575_31</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863351</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91886)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E575[31])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse between monarchical and aristocratical government. Or a sober perswasive of all true-hearted Englishmen, to a willing conjunction with the Parliament of England in setting up the government of a common-wealth. By a true Englishman, and well-wisher to the good of this nation.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop at the three Daggers neer the Inner-Temple, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A true Englishman = Henry Robinson.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 24th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Republics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165455:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SHORT DISCOURSE BETWEEN MONARCHICAL AND ARISTOCRATICAL Government.</p>
            <p>Or a Sober perſwaſive of all true-hearted Engliſhmen, to a willing conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> In ſetting up the Government of a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>By a true Engliſhman, and Well-wiſher to the good of this NATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad juga cur faciles populi cur ſaeva volentes Regna pati; Pereunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quoniam non contenti certa libertate in dubiam imperii ſervitiique aleam imus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 SAM. 8. 6, 7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>In asking a King, they have not rejected me, but thee, that I ſhould not raign over them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the three Daggers neer the <hi>Inner-Temple, Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:165455:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165455:2"/>
            <head>A Short Diſcourſe BETWEEN MONARCHICAL, AND ARISTOCRATICAL Government.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not to be expected by any wiſe, or conſiderate perſon, to finde an exact Logical ſeries, or Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Demonſtration in Publike or Political Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions; In which, as there are commonly many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known difficulties to be waded through, ſo there are multitudes of emergencies (not poſſible to be be foreſeen) dayly breaking forth, which give cauſe, as of altering mens thoughts, ſo of changing, and ſhifting the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums,</hi> by which they ſhould have been at firſt effected. Nor can it be imagined, That the abſolute order of Nature ſhould be ſtrictly kept in theſe affairs, which only <hi>Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> Govern.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165455:3"/>
            <p> The want of ſuch like conſiderations as theſe, hath been a great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diſcontents, and diſaffections of the moſt ſpirits, concerning the management of the great concernment of this Nation. Some have looked more after <hi>Modum,</hi> then <hi>Rem,</hi> the circumſtance, then the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; rather how things are done, then what is done, thinking nothing well done, but what they have either been predominant inſtruments in themſelves, or elſe could Analitically reſolve, according to the rule of their own prejudiced apprehenſions. It is to be acknowledged, That of late (through the Apoſtacy of ſome, and the Indifferency of others, and the change of many ſpirits by cunning, yet Malignant influences) our affaires in this Nation, for the external, and circumſtantial acting of them, have not gone one ſo ſmoothly, or takingly unto every ſpirit; preſent neceſſity, abſolute conveniency, and providence (which eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally hath had a ſupremacy over them) putting us on many ſuddain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures, and to leap over many leſſer things (which ſome think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable) yea, hath forc'd us to do much at once, and to haſten on to theſe works, which at another time, and in ſome other caſes, would have admitted many ſteps and degrees, in the attaining of them. Though it's no great diſadvantage to a work, if it be done throughly, that it's done ſuddainly, and expeditiouſly; yea, many times, more time and coſt is ſpent in a Ceremony, then by diligent proſecution of advantages, would be to attain the thing it ſelf. As in great mens houſes, the paint and the hangings, coſt more then the houſe it ſelf. But beſides, the nature of ſome affairs call for a doing them now or never; and men being remote from the Actors, and ſo unacquainted with the preſent grounds, and reaſons on which they are acted, ſtorm at that, which they themſelves in the ſame caſe, and on the ſame principles, would be moſt forward to attempt; not conſidering (until it come to their own caſes) That where men have to deal with humors, as well as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with Forces, and Fictions, with general, and particular, Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, Divided, and Sub-divided Intereſts, ſome ſpecial liberty muſt be given, to act according to preſent overtures, and ſome occult reaſons pre-ſuppoſed, which every eye cannot, nor may not look into.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed; He that with a ſober, and untainted judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſiders the late Tranſactions of the Parliament, and Army, with the King, Their own members, and the changing of the former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, into a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> hath more reaſon to be aſtoniſhed at what is done, then be diſcontented at the way, and manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; no man being able to imagine, That by any means what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165455:3"/> we ſhould have been able to attain to the condition we are now in, and eſpecially not ſo ſuddenly, and with ſo much advantage, to free our ſelves from ſuch a yoke, that neither our fathers nor we were able to bear; and certainly had not there bin ſomething divine in it, (which men care not to obſerve) and had not the finger of the <hi>Almighty</hi> wrought it for us, we had been far from ſo much as a hope of recovery, and ere this day had been reduced to a worſe bondage then ever <hi>England</hi> yet ſaw<hi>:</hi> And if we will conſider what ſtraits and extremities they have been often put unto, by the falſeneſs of ſome, and the folly of others, what varieties of difficulties they have been encompaſſed about with, through the malice of the common enemy, and the imprudence of their own friends, and ſubtle deſigns of many pretented <hi>Patriots,</hi> we ſhall ſee cauſe enough to wonder where we are come, and by what a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſtrain of providence they have been carryed on to this happy change: And however things may be repreſented in the Glaſſes of <hi>Malignant and humorous Spirits,</hi> yet if men will make uſe of a plain <hi>Optique,</hi> and not look through their <hi>PASSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS</hi> or <hi>ENGAGEMENTS,</hi> they will ſee no ſuch <hi>Diſproportion</hi> between the firſt <hi>PRINCIPLE</hi> of this <hi>WAR,</hi> and the preſent actings of things, eſpecially (conſidering how we have been led into them) though the firſt Inſtruments could not ſee the ultimate end at ſo great a diſtance of time, and through ſo many mountains of difficulties that lay in their way: God himſelf alſo is (who loves to <hi>non-plus</hi> the beſt of men) by his providence acting his own deſigns, beyond the firſt motions and intentions of men.</p>
            <p>As the firſt beginnings of all things are uſually fair and modeſt, ſo were they among us in the beginning of this War; and though our firſt principle was fundamental, and large enough, when we took up Arms, <hi>viz. The Liberties of this Nation,</hi> from that Tyrannical Power which was exerciſed by the late <hi>King,</hi> and for the ſetting up a free Court of Juſtice in the <hi>Nation,</hi> in order to which, care was taken to put the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> in the beſt hands we could find, yet the hopes we then had of a ſudden effecting it, and that by the firſt means we could uſe, and the controverſie being ſuddenly to be debated, and honeſt men not ſo well acquainted with their own priviledges, nor the ground of the quarrel, the Parliament was conſtrained to expreſs great reſpects to the <hi>King,</hi> and to ſtate the difference very tenderly, and put all the weight of miſcarriages on his Councel, ſalving as much as they could his honour, yea made many Engagements for advancing of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165455:4"/> Grandure and Majeſty, which was carefully kept and obſerved, as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intended, until that the neceſſity of affairs grew on, and the <hi>King</hi> took advantage by all reſpects to harden his own heart, and had quite changed his own condition from what it was when theſe Engagements were made; yea, almoſt all the <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>ſpirits</hi> of men, both in <hi>Parliament, City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> being altered, by the ſubtle Inſinuations of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Agents,</hi> and not only a firſt but ſecond War levyed by the <hi>Kings Commiſſion</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> more dangerous then the former, though miraculouſly paſt over: It was now time to take the advantage of providence, and make uſe of that honeſt power yet left to proſecute our firſt <hi>principles</hi> to the beſt end, and go through with that which we did but dally with before; and ſeeing that the <hi>King</hi> was the only cauſe of the firſt and ſecond War, and of corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all <hi>intereſts</hi> and <hi>ſpirits</hi> which ever came nigh him, and that his evil Councel (on whom all was formerly laid) was ſequeſtred from him, and yet the ſame things and worſe done by him, could imagine no other Expedient to preſerve the <hi>Nation,</hi> but by removing the prime cauſe of their miſery; and ſeeing the diſeaſe was grown deſperate to apply a remedy proportionable. That if any thing have been acted, that ſeems <hi>Heterodox</hi> to our firſt Intentions and Engagements, it hath been but to follow the <hi>King,</hi> who fruſtrated all our hopes, and grew to be ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and implacable an Enemy, that he left us no other remedy but his death to give us any hope of recovery. And now you ſee that we are like to attain our End, Liberty and Juſtice, though we could not at firſt ſee the way how, and it's brought about by other <hi>mediums</hi> then we firſt intended it; neither is any diſparagement to us, that our <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are procured by ſuch a <hi>Royal Sacrifice.</hi> But it is in vain to repeat; Thoſe which ſtumble ſo much at that unparaleld, and moſt <hi>glorious act of Juſtice</hi> done on the late <hi>King,</hi> may be deſired to conſider, what way elſe was left us to preſerve the honeſt party of this <hi>Nation,</hi> yea the whole <hi>Nation</hi> beſides; and to prefer the life of our grand Enemy before the good of a <hi>Nation,</hi> is fooliſh pity indeed: for that our <hi>Liberty</hi> and his <hi>life</hi> were grown to be incompetible, and inconſiſtent, is moſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative, ſeeing he was not ſo much as ſenſible of any miſcarriages, nor repented of a drop of blood ſhed ſo plentifully by his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> but grew ſo hardned, that he would rather dye, then conſent to theſe abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and juſt grounds of <hi>Liberty and Safety</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſo often ſent him, in order to his advancement, and the ſecurity of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> What ever had been done beſides, would have been but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165455:4"/> the skinning over the wound while it did inwardly feſter and gangrene, and have given our Enemies advantage to undo us by our own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, which they could not by their open hoſtility and force.</p>
            <p>But I am ſorry I have detained the Reader ſo long from a ready com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with this preſent <hi>Government,</hi> by repeating the miſeries of the old: But it's good ſometimes to look back, that we may ſee what Mercies we enjoy at preſent. For my part, I cannot but think that <hi>Scaffold</hi> ſacred, and no other Sacrifice could have been ſo expiatory before God, or men, for that Blood which hath been ſhed in this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then His who was the onely cauſe of it; And yet I cannot blame thoſe that think him to be above Law, ſhould judg him to be above puniſhment: And though, unto ſome tender ſpirits, it may ſeem hard, and of ill conſequence, yet, upon ſecond thoughts, they will ſee it neceſſary, and juſt, and the fruits anſwerable, if our new <hi>diſcontexts,</hi> as well as former <hi>pity,</hi> and <hi>indulgence,</hi> do not fruſtrate it: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our <hi>Ancestors,</hi> were they alive, would admire their <hi>Childrens</hi> fortunes and happineſs, who have had the opportunity to act that, which they thought (but durſt not ſpeak) would be their greateſt Mercy, <hi>viz. To caſt off that uſurped Government, which they felt the Tyranny and Oppreſſion of ſo many years, without hope of Remedy.</hi> But if any thing of Conſcience ſhould be in that, your diſſent and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting may ſatisfie you, and their acting againſt them, who held their Judgments well informed, and acted accordingly in that great and impartial work of Juſtice: Let us therefore forget theſe things which are impoſſible to be helped, and fall on to thoſe things which are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and neceſſary; and labor to be as conſcientious in avoyding ways of making new Diviſions, as we are in remembering former Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages: We are now (through providence) on a new Foundation, and have time to conſider our own good, and want nothing to make us the happieſt <hi>Nation</hi> under the Sun, but the bleſſing of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> which yet we have, (and are like to have it ſhine in greater ſplendor,) and a hearty and free compliance with the <hi>Government</hi> now ſet up, by all honeſt and ingenuous men, who mean to ſhare in the fruits of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> together.</p>
            <p>And truly Prudence and Reaſon, that teacheth men to make ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of neceſſities, may well make men ingenuous in improving advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages and conveniences. I know there are many ſorts of men to be delt with in this <hi>paranatick:</hi> Some who can onely be perſwaded by force and violence, as <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>debauched ſpirits;</hi> and we can onely
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165455:5"/> ſecure their perſons, hardly ever gain their conſents, they have drank ſo deeply of that cup of deluſion: Yet the remembrance of their former Compoſitions may poſſibly aw them, and ſcrue them into obedience. I have better matter to deal withal in this Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> with honeſt hearts, which are either miſcarryed through deceitful pretences, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented through miſtaken apprehenſions, or have been at leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartened through want of obſervance of Gods actings in theſe affairs, and ſo ſit at too great a diſtance from compliance with this preſent <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment:</hi> For it's moſt true, that as many men get their own ends through pretence of Religion, ſo others weakly look on Religion through the diſguizes of cunning Politicians, which they converſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. And it hath been a great miſery to our Cauſe, That honeſt men have, either in the actings of things, conſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed too much with fleſh and blood, or ſuffered themſelves to be abuſed by the ſpecious inſinuations of thoſe men, who have had no reſerve of honor and reſpect, but what they could get by ſuch ſtratagems. I dare not undertake to plead for any perſon, or party, or to juſtifie men in any thing; I am now pleading for a common good, by a convenient <hi>Government,</hi> (though I know no reaſon why men ſhould diſ-affect good things out of any prejudice to parties and perſons). I can love Gold, though in the Oar, and prize Diamonds, though unfiled and unſet: But to the thing. It is not onely to be wiſhed and deſired, but that which all honeſt men (who love the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and deſire to ſee but any comfortable iſſue of theſe late ſad Diſtractions) ſhould be engaged in, unanimouſly to cloſe in with the preſent Overtures, and promote, by all means and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, the <hi>Government</hi> ſet up by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and laying aſide all particular animoſities, and waving leſſer differences, paſs an Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion for all former miſcarriages, whether real or ſuppoſed, and take the advantage of advancing our good by the preſent opportunity, having cauſe to fear, that if we neglect this, we ſhall never enjoy the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for <hi>Truth and Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leaſt men might pretend Conſcience or Reaſon to countenance their diſ-affection to this <hi>Government of a Commonwealth,</hi> I ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entreat honeſt men to conſider, That there is no ſuch ſupernatural ſtamp, or <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> ſet on <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> which ſhould engage mens hearts unto it ſo peculiarly, more then on any other, excepting onely ſuch a <hi>State</hi> which hath not form and order in it. What ever mens affections may be to one Government more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I know not, but there is no Divine Character of reſpect more on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165455:5"/> one then other; But God, who is a God of Order, hath ordained <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,</hi> and delights to ſee his <hi>Creatures</hi> made happy by them, and therefore hath left them to chooſe what they think may be moſt fit for that end, and to call it by what name they pleaſe; and that <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which is in one place called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an Ordinance of God,</hi> is in another called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a creature, or institution of man,</hi> the power it ſelf being from God, the diſtinction and perſonal admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration from man; and if it were not ſo, no <hi>Government</hi> but one could be lawful, or to be obeyed by any people as an Ordinance of <hi>God:</hi> And by conſequence, if <hi>Monarchy</hi> have this impreſsion onely from Heaven no <hi>Government</hi> but that is to be accounted lawful, or obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it from any <hi>ſpiritual rule</hi> but <hi>force and neceſſity,</hi> which not any that hath his veins never ſo full of royal blood will maintain. Thoſe that take the <hi>divinity</hi> of Regal power from its ſimilitude and likeneſs it hath unto God and his Supremacy, and oneneſs in the <hi>Government</hi> of the World, plead rather for the <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> or <hi>Ruſſian Monarchy,</hi> then for <hi>Englands,</hi> they holding for a more exact likeneſs to God (in their ſence) ruling all by their own wills independently from any; whereas onely that <hi>Government</hi> hath Gods heart in it ſpecially which is founded in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and propagated by <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and doth moſt bleſs a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> But if men will refer the judgment of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> to what God ſays of it when it was firſt mentioned to him by his own People, as deſirous to be under it, it's moſt obſervable (though I would not make it an argument) That no diſtinct <hi>Order of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> had ever ſuch a ſignal blur, and ſtamp of diſlike from God, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> nor did ever any people receive a publique check from Heaven for chooſing any <hi>Government,</hi> but <hi>King-ſhip;</hi> and it ſtands on re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to this day, that God was diſpleaſed but at the <hi>motion of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael to have a King,</hi> as the <hi>Heathens,</hi> they being not content with the wiſdom of God, who choſe another <hi>Government</hi> for them, as better, and more fit for honeſt and godly men, he gave them a <hi>King,</hi> but in <hi>wrath.</hi> And if God were ſo diſpleaſed with them, but for ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a King after the manner of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> which King God himſelf ſhould have a vote in the choyce of, how will he be with us, who will have a King which God hath rejected.</p>
            <p>But though many good hearts may think the <hi>jus divinum</hi> to be alike, yet they may finde many Obligations to <hi>Kingly Government</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> which are ſacred, and may lie on their Conſciences as an impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a full cloſing with this <hi>Government,</hi> which they may in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165455:6"/> Reaſon be convinced is fit and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>I confeſs there is nothing of more reverence in the eyes of any ſerious ſpirit then ſolemn <hi>Oaths and Covenants,</hi> whereby men are obliged to God as well as men, and have their Conſciences to anſwer as well as Reaſon: Yet there may be too ſcruplous a Conſcience, and many times Conſcience is made too great a pretence and covert for <hi>inward malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and diſlike of things themſelves. Yet what ever pretence men may make of their <hi>Obligation by Oath to another Government,</hi> ſuch <hi>Oaths</hi> cannot be binding now, when not onely the <hi>perſons,</hi> but the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it ſelf is removed; the very Commands of God, which are affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, binde not <hi>ad ſemper</hi> to all times and particular movements; and I hope no godly man thinks any other <hi>Covenant</hi> to be everlaſting, but the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> We all grant, that no <hi>Oath</hi> bindes me when I am dead, neither can any <hi>Oath</hi> binde me to dead perſons, or things not in being; and what ever <hi>Oaths</hi> men have taken, relating to the perſon of the <hi>late King,</hi> or that <hi>Government,</hi> cannot be in force, but muſt needs be out of date, and unobliging, when the perſon is dead, and the <hi>Government</hi> it ſelf neceſſarily altered; eſpecially when the matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which the <hi>Oath</hi> made is civil and changeable, and made not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, but conditionally, as the late <hi>Covenant</hi> was, we binding our ſelves <hi>to preſerve his Majesties perſon, &amp;c. in the Preſervation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberty,</hi> which we have found abſolutely contrary, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent together. And let me ſay, it were to be wiſhed, that this <hi>tenderneſs of Conſcience</hi> were in ſome of the ſcruplers about this <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> formerly, when the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was firſt urged, the matters of which were ſacred, as well as the <hi>Oath</hi> it ſelf, and yet nothing would then ſerve, but <hi>force and violence, baniſhment,</hi> with many ſuch <hi>threats,</hi> to thoſe that would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it, the matter and manner of which belonged properly to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and was controverted by the beſt and ableſt men, and yet a rational diſſent by one ſide entred, and the thing it ſelf hardly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in ſome points: But I am for union, and may not open old ſores: It's well the Cauſe is changed, and the Tryal come about to others, that they may know what Conſcience means Yet it's ſtill to be deſired, that men would conſider, what ſin againſt any mans <hi>Conſcience</hi> it can be, to joyn in with a <hi>Government,</hi> which is not onely moſt lawful in it ſelf, but moſt neceſſary at preſent? or how they can in Conſcience (without ſome other Reaſon) maintain their <hi>engagements</hi> to a <hi>non-entity?</hi> or how they can diſcharge their <hi>Conſcience</hi> from one <hi>ſin,</hi> by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165455:6"/> doing <hi>another?</hi> or make an <hi>atonement</hi> for preſent diſobedience to an Ordinance of God, (as every <hi>Government</hi> in it ſelf is) by former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Obligation</hi> to that which they have not at preſent, or, it may be, never ſhall have <hi>opportunity</hi> to perform.</p>
            <p>I know the <hi>Parliament</hi> will have regard to <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> and lay nothing which may be a <hi>burthen</hi> on them: But it will be very ſad and ominous, that all mens <hi>malignity and ſtate-distempers</hi> ſhould have ſuch a plauſible diſguize as <hi>Conſcience;</hi> or that neceſſary and civil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which are but reductively and ſecondarily belonging to <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> ſhould be ſimple, and abſolutely deſtroyed by ſuch a plea, which is common to one as well as another. But I doubt not but that the juſtneſs and honeſt fruits of this <hi>Government</hi> will end at mens hearts to it, as their former <hi>Engagements,</hi> or rather <hi>diſ-affections,</hi> have made men conſciencious againſt it.</p>
            <p>And now ſeeing that there is no more <hi>divinity</hi> in one <hi>Government</hi> more then another, and former Obligations dye with the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that our <hi>Conſciences</hi> (rightly informed) cannot be bound by them, let us conſider our conveniencies, and reflect on Kingly power in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and the ſad fruits and effects of it, eſpecially of late, and we ſhall ſee little reaſon of being ſo endeared to it, much leſs to dote on it as we do. How nigh were all our Liberties to give up the ghoſt under it? What bloody and cruel <hi>attempts</hi> have there been made by it on the Souls, Eſtates, and perſons of many thouſands in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> but onely to pleaſe the will or luſt of one <hi>Tyrant?</hi> We have felt too much of this, and I need not repeat; Theſe have been the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural off-springs</hi> of that <hi>Government,</hi> not onely here, but in all <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> no people living in peace under it, but thoſe which are quietly content either with no <hi>Liberty,</hi> or but with onely the ſhadow or name of it; I may affirm it by all Hiſtories univerſally, <hi>That Royalty and Liberty have never heartily embraced each other, or have ſhined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame ſplendor or beauty, but one hath either quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, or eclipſed the others glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God himſelf (who beſt knew the <hi>nature of all Governments,</hi> and fore-ſaw their effects) makes <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> very neer of kin, and as ſoon as ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have a King, tells them what they muſt neceſſarily expect, as inſeparable adjuncts or effects of it, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 11. 12, 13.) <hi>This ſhall be the manner of the King which ſhall reign over you, he will take your ſons and appoint them for himſelf, for his Charets, and Horſemen, and ſome ſhall run before his Charets;</hi> with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165455:7"/> many other expreſſions of like nature, all the fruits of <hi>Tyranny</hi> which can be imagined, and all this inſeparably annexed to it, by the foreſight of God himſelf. Yea, <hi>Liberty and Monarchy</hi> have been ever ſo <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competible,</hi> That in the beſt Hiſtories of <hi>that Government,</hi> they have been not only <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> but <hi>oppoſed;</hi> eſpecially, thoſe that look over the <hi>Roman Hiſtories</hi> (who had experience of both) will find, when <hi>Kingly Power began to flouriſh, LIBERTY</hi> decayed, and ſo <hi>è contra. Tacitus Annal.</hi> 1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem Romam ab initio Reges ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buere, Libertatem &amp; Conſulatum,</hi> L. Brutus <hi>inſtituit. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans had firſt KINGS, but</hi> L. Brutus <hi>brought in Liberty, and the Conſulſhip:</hi> So <hi>Livy</hi> Lib. 45. <hi>Non in Regno Populam Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſed in Libertate eſſe;</hi> and the ſame Author <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Regem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebant Libertatis dulcedine nondum experta: None love Kingly Government, or can deſire to be under it, but thoſe that never taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſweets of Liberty.</hi> And ſhall we now ſtrive to joyn thoſe two together in our expectations, which (I had almoſt ſaid) <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> have divided, I am ſure all Nations have had experience of inconſiſtency of? Have we ventured ſo hard, for to gain our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſhall not we now take the advantage of procuring them? Or do we think that ſlavery is any whit the more amiable, becauſe it hath the name of <hi>Royalty</hi> annexed to it? If we be not yet ſenſible of our condition, we may hereafter; when ſome have got their wills, we ſhall have our eyes opened, though it be but to ſee our miſery, when paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> hath many more curbs, and bridles on it to reſtrain it from <hi>Exorbitancy,</hi> then can be ſet on <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and is ſo leſs capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing miſchief to a <hi>Nation</hi> then the other. The diſtance of their place, the remoteneſs of <hi>Princes</hi> from <hi>vulgar ſight,</hi> the many <hi>ſcreens</hi> they have between them and the people, and that great reverence they get by their retiredneſs from ordinary converſe, give them <hi>unavoidable advantages</hi> of doing that more <hi>ſecretly,</hi> and <hi>effectually,</hi> and with leſs <hi>guilt,</hi> then can be imagined to be done by a <hi>Publique State,</hi> who are more open to the view of the world, and are but themſelves in power, <hi>quam ain bene ſe geſſerint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen of late, how hard it hath been but to make the people think the <hi>King could offend,</hi> or was liable to <hi>any guilt, or charge,</hi> laying all on his <hi>Councel,</hi> while he was the <hi>Malignant Genius</hi> that led them; and yet being ſo much out of <hi>ſight,</hi> ſo far off from <hi>Popular view,</hi> went free for a long time from any poſitive charge, and had gone to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165455:7"/> this day as an <hi>Innocent one,</hi> and one uncapable of <hi>Spot, or blame,</hi> had not God ſtirred up ſuch a ſpirit of <hi>courage and Justice in that rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of faithful Patriots,</hi> who have <hi>Anatomiz'd his wicked, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical practiſes before all the world, and done ſutable juſtice on him for it;</hi> And yet the old <hi>Maxims,</hi> received by <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> and invented by his <hi>Paraſites,</hi> and <hi>Favourites, (That the King can do no wrong, That he is accountable to none but God for his Actions)</hi> lie in the breſt of moſt men, as <hi>Orthodox Law, and Gospel,</hi> and will be ſoon embraced again, and reprinted in a larger <hi>Character,</hi> if ever the ſame power be ſet up again, though never ſo contrary to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Liberty;</hi> yea, the late King himſelf ſealed the confirmation of them with his own Blood, and therefore would not plead, or anſwer any thing to <hi>the High Court of Juſtice,</hi> not ſo much becauſe he thought the <hi>Authority</hi> of it to be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal, as that he thought himſelf <hi>above the judgment of any Authority on earth;</hi> and would have doubtleſs refuſed to have anſwered to <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> though in a full houſe, and in one <hi>Judicature,</hi> if they ſhould have laid ſuch a Charge againſt him; for in his former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, he was ſo far from owning their <hi>Authority,</hi> That he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed both Houſes (when in their full <hi>power and grandure) Traytors and Rebels,</hi> becauſe they ſate <hi>without his preſence;</hi> and yet we have thought ours but a limited, and bounded <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what hopes we can have of <hi>Kingly power in this Nation,</hi> which is founded on ſuch principles, and propagated on the ſame terms, let wiſe and honeſt men judge.</p>
            <p>Beſides, when we have moſt ſolemnly conſidered <hi>Monarchy in its real uſe and end,</hi> it will be found to be in effect but an <hi>Aristocracy,</hi> though far more dangerous and miſchievous; The ſame things are done, as to the <hi>good of the Publique,</hi> by <hi>States and Councels,</hi> which are done by <hi>Kings and Councels</hi> together; and either the King <hi>muſt rule by his own will,</hi> and then he is a <hi>profest Tyrant,</hi> or elſe by <hi>Counſel of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and <hi>Publique Senators,</hi> and then it's the <hi>Councel</hi> that rules the Kingdom, who can do it as well, and with leſs hazard, without him; As being free from the <hi>Temptations of Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Royal favours,</hi> whereby the beſt of men (ere they were aware) have been corrupted, and the wiſeſt <hi>Counſellors</hi> ſuborned to act ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Regal intereſt,</hi> contrary to the <hi>good of the Common-wealth;</hi> whereas, while they act in a <hi>Parity among themſelves,</hi> as their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are moſt free from being acted by <hi>Superior influences,</hi> ſo their <hi>Debates,</hi> and <hi>Reſults,</hi> muſt needs be of more common and publique
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165455:8"/> concernment, they themſelves, having an equal ſhare in that <hi>good,</hi> which is done unto the whole.</p>
            <p>That if we do but caſt up our accounts right, we ſhall find that Kings are but meer chargeable <hi>Ceremonies, or Ciphers,</hi> of little uſe but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract humors, and promote perſonal deſigns deſtructive to the being, and well-being of <hi>Common-wealths;</hi> for they neither are executioners of juſtice themſelves, nay, ſcarce (many times) <hi>Counſellors,</hi> nor do any ſpecial or publique work; and yet for meer cuſtom and formalities ſake, we muſt have one man adored, having a ſupreme power inveſted in him, and be maintained in the greateſt <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> meerly to ſit ſtill and have the beſt, and wiſeſt, and moſt faithful, and gallant inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments bow down, and rejoyce, <hi>but to kiſs his hand.</hi> If any King hath ever yet been more then ordinarily active, or inſtrumental, it hath been to proſecute ſome deſign which would advance his Supremacy more Independently againſt the <hi>Publique Good,</hi> as the late King was in his <hi>Wars</hi> againſt this Nation.</p>
            <p>And what ever other Nations may experiment, if we have found any good by <hi>Monarchy</hi> in this <hi>Nation,</hi> it is, that it hath made us (I hope) know what Liberty and Law is, and to prize them the more; <hi>Quae liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ut laetior eſſet proximi Regis ſuperbia ſaceret, Which Liberty we ſhould eſteem more, had we but one tryal of the next KINGS Raign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as there is nothing more <hi>vertually,</hi> and <hi>really</hi> in <hi>Monarchical</hi> then what is in <hi>Ariſtocratical Government,</hi> and nothing to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the one, but what may be done by the other with leſs fear of danger, and without ſuch coſtly formality: So <hi>Ariſtocracy, (or this Government of a Common-wealth the Parliament have ſet up)</hi> is the moſt even, and <hi>juſt Government,</hi> that any men have yet come to the knowledge of, it being a middle <hi>State</hi> between <hi>Popular Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> and <hi>Prerogative Tyranny,</hi> whereby men are freed from the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>exorbitancies of both,</hi> and ſeated ſecurely in a <hi>uniform and equal condition</hi> free from all extreams, in which the people are <hi>beſt repreſented,</hi> and by which the Laws and <hi>dispatches of Juſtice,</hi> and other affairs have a quicker and eaſier paſſage, with leſs noiſe, &amp; Tumult, then if they ſhould run down from the high mountains of <hi>Prerogative and Majeſty,</hi> in the diſpenſations of which, you have little cogniſance of <hi>juſtice, or reaſon,</hi> but of <hi>grace, and favor;</hi> Kings and Princes ſeldom granting any thing, though never ſo juſt, but it's ever as from <hi>grace,</hi> ſo with an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomething from the people to advance their <hi>Prerogative,</hi> the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165455:8"/> doing of which may be a greater loſs, and hazard, then the former grant could be of concernment to them.</p>
            <p>But in this other <hi>Government,</hi> as juſtice runs more <hi>ſmoothly,</hi> and <hi>clearer,</hi> and is not painted with <hi>Royal colours,</hi> ſo the people have a more immediate way to the redreſs of all their <hi>grievanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and are not forc'd as to clime too high, ſo not to go to far about, or through ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>mercenary Favourites,</hi> or rooms of <hi>State,</hi> or be ſcar'd with the ſuddain <hi>beams of ſuppoſed Majeſty,</hi> but come to their own <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> that themſelves have choſen, and who may be in the ſame condition, and are to be tryed by the ſame Laws themſelves, which they for the preſent judge others by. And it's obſervable, Theſe few <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which have once got the opportunity (which ſome have ventured hard for with little ſucceſs) of caſting off <hi>Kingly Power,</hi> have natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and out of choice, fallen into this <hi>Government,</hi> as the middle, and beſt, and that which was moſt ſafe, and <hi>ſutable to Liberty and Justice;</hi> and how theſe <hi>Nations</hi> which have been under it have flouriſhed, I could mention (if it were needful) in <hi>multitudes of teſtimonies;</hi> And not to go ſo far back unto the <hi>Roman State,</hi> that little time it enjoyed it; Let us view theſe little ſpots of Land in <hi>Europe</hi> that live under this <hi>Government,</hi> how do they lift up their heads in <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>wealth,</hi> above all their neighbours, to name no more but the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and <hi>Venice;</hi> The firſt, even on a ſuddain, even by it's Wars againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> enriching of it ſelf beyond many Kingdoms of <hi>ten times a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger continent;</hi> and the other defending it ſelf, yea, <hi>annoying one of the greateſt Empires under the Sun.</hi> And there is no reaſon why <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhould not flouriſh under it much more,</hi> who hath a more <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral defence</hi> of it ſelf, then other places have, and more reaſon, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſetting it up, then any other people have yet had; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>Climate,</hi> and <hi>Air,</hi> is not <hi>incompetible</hi> to it. Had other <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> but the <hi>Liberty to ſpeak,</hi> and the <hi>Freedom to chooſe</hi> as we have, we ſhould ſoon hear which way the <hi>Vote</hi> would go.</p>
            <p>But let it be found out (as a <hi>Phoenix)</hi> That ſome <hi>Nations</hi> have had <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> under the Raign of ſome <hi>Kings,</hi> which were of ſingular tempers and vertues; or, it may be, had not time enough, or opportunity, both to plot and act deſigns together; yet when <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhal come to be <hi>hereditary,</hi> &amp; <hi>Regal Power</hi> advanced by <hi>ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> there muſt needs be unknown miſchiefs propagated together with it: And all mens <hi>liberties</hi> are caſt away on a peradventure at the beſt; for be he young or old, wiſe or unwiſe, vertuous or vicious, <hi>talis, qualis,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165455:9"/> he muſt be entruſted with all the <hi>Liberties</hi> (it may be, of many <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,)</hi> and a neceſſity of bondage and miſery, without remedy, ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively entailed on men and their poſterity: All <hi>liberty</hi> of diſſent or choice (which is the birth right of rational and free-men) being utterly denyed to them, and deſtroyed by a titular plea of ſucceſſion to that which, it may be, the perſon is neither fit for the mannagement of, being a child, or weak, or worthy of, through vice, or ill converſation.</p>
            <p>And however other <hi>Nations</hi> may, out of hidden ſecrets of <hi>State,</hi> think <hi>Monarchy</hi> beſt for them, and be willing to venture at ſucceſſion, yet to us it would not be only inconvenient, but miſchievous; Having juſtly cut off the Fathers head for a wicked and ill <hi>Goverment,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne the Son, who was engaged in the ſame quarrel, and hath enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſame <hi>principles,</hi> with an addition of more malice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; and what were it but to give that power to undo us, which we (through the providence of God) have happily deprived his Father of? For as we had no hopes of the late King, but were in continual danger of taking advantages by us; ſo we cannot have any probable expectation from his Son, who was engaged Body and Soul in his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Interest,</hi> and trained up from his cradle in blood, who, beſides his Youth, (and ſo his unfitneſs to manage the Affairs of ſuch a <hi>State,)</hi> hath a double portion of his Fathers Spirit of Pride and Tyranny on him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Mothers bleſſing, and is the perfect and natural Heir to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Quarrel and Deſign, as to his Crown and Dignity.</p>
            <p>But the great thing to be wondred at, is, That any which love <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Government</hi> ſhould dote on <hi>Monarchy,</hi> eſpecially after the Raign of ſuch a perſon, and ſtand out againſt this <hi>Government</hi> which the <hi>Parliament</hi> have now ſet up. <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> in <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> do not run ſo paralel in the expreſſions, what ever they may do in the ſence. <hi>Kingly Government</hi> hath never been yet very propitious, or benign to <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> the moſt favour it hath got in any <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is but to have a Toleration, as in <hi>France,</hi> and in this <hi>Nation;</hi> it's hardly a probationer: but <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> hath been that ancient <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which hath been bred up with <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and hath of late been its greateſt Darling, to maintain which, much of the <hi>Royal Intereſt</hi> hath been engaged; the late <hi>King</hi> making one of the grounds of his War to be the taking away of that <hi>Government,</hi> which he thought to be ſo fundamental and ſacred, that all <hi>Religion</hi> was wrapt up in it, and to confirm his love unto it, dyed with a Biſhop in his arms. And ſuch inſeparable union is between <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that King
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165455:9"/> 
               <hi>James</hi> himſelf, as ſoon as ever he came out of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> (and found himſelf to be a <hi>King)</hi> made this State Maxime, <hi>No Biſhop no King,</hi> which is to this day unrepealed, and by experience confirmed, for they have both dyed together as Twins in the boſom of each other; and if we do but look a little back, we ſhall find, that <hi>Preſbyterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> never thrived well, no not in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (the moſt fertile ſoil, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural climate wherein it flouriſheth moſt) until the <hi>King</hi> was removed at ſuch a diſtance; and yet what attempts have both <hi>King James</hi> and <hi>Charls</hi> made, but to overthrow it in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as being moſt unſuitable to <hi>Kingly Government?</hi> and they have little cauſe to think, that their <hi>Charls the Second</hi> will forget his Grand-fathers and Fathers Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy.</p>
            <p>And now we have begun to mention <hi>Scotland,</hi> it may be ſome may bring in them as a preſident to us, (as formerly to the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo now to the <hi>State,)</hi> who, notwithſtanding all their inconveniencies, which they have found by <hi>Monarchy,</hi> yet have thought fit to continue it, and that in the right line of Succeſſion: It's well known, the <hi>Scots</hi> love the Name, but care little for the Company or Power of a <hi>King;</hi> Neither is it much to be admired, that they ſhould proclaim <hi>King</hi> whom they never intend ſhall rule over them; for they well know how to make uſe of the Name, though they mean not to ſubject to the Power: The <hi>Scots</hi> are not a <hi>Nation</hi> of as much ſtate and riches as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> but of as much deſign as any, and they well fore-ſee, that whoſe <hi>King</hi> ſoever he be, <hi>England</hi> muſt maintain him, and bear the greateſt burthen, while they enjoy his ſmall Revenue in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and get places and penſions from him in <hi>England,</hi> ſo that he muſt be their <hi>King,</hi> but our <hi>Tyrant:</hi> All that underſtand the Affairs of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> know, that were it not for the name of the <hi>King,</hi> the factions of their <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> are ſo great, that Peace could never be kept among themſelves, and yet if they had a <hi>King</hi> really among them, it would impoveriſh both Gentry and Nobility, who muſt contribute to maintain him, who in <hi>England</hi> by penſions and places hath ſet up them. But I would not too much open the nakedneſs of that Nation, but wiſh them much good with their King, and his hideous train of Malignants, which muſt neceſſarily follow him where ever he himſelf is entertained with any reſpect or honor: Onely they ſhould have given him title to their own Nation, and have left our Parliament to have choſen for us, who are come to ſufficient years of diſcretion, and have learnt to underſtand both their King and them; but it ſeems it would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165455:10"/> profit them little to have him King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> if he were not alſo of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> It is for us to conſult our own concernments, and not trouble our ſelves with examples: If we chance to differ from other <hi>States,</hi> it's becauſe they have not the ſame advantages, nor we the ſame cauſes and grounds of following them. All that is propoſed by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is, to reduce us into a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and if the name do not offend, I know not why ſhould the thing.</p>
            <p>And as to that reverent plea of the Antiquity of <hi>Monarchy</hi> in this Nation, we may anſwer with grief, it hath been too long; and we have had time enough to try and feel the ſad effects of it; and Kingſhip may very well, after ſo long a perſonal reign and advancement of it ſelf, give way to a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> that the <hi>Nation</hi> may get ſome good, and enjoy ſome <hi>Liberty,</hi> after their long ſervitude to it. <hi>Antiquity</hi> is an argument for nothing but <hi>truth and goodneſs,</hi> elſe error and uſurpation will plead its gray hairs, and make a demonſtration of its <hi>divinity</hi> with the beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>And wheras many wiſe men object the danger of changes in <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> &amp; the unknown conſequences which may follow, it's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and therefore the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath took time and deliberation, and tryed all <hi>expedients;</hi> and made the beſt eſſays for ſecurity of the <hi>Nation</hi> without it; But that change cannot be dangerous, where the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of a former <hi>Government,</hi> in ſuch perſons, hath proved, and is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably miſchievous, as it is in our cauſe; and yet we have not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our Laws, or the Fundamentals of the former <hi>Government,</hi> but onely the perſons and <hi>mal-adminiſtrators</hi> of it; that it's but a change of perſons and names, which have acted, and are like to act to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſo hinder miſchief from running in a blood: And if we will with ſeriouſneſs and obſervance look about us, we may diſcern a <hi>bright Star of Providence</hi> leading us directly to it, and a harmony of wonders and mercies accompanying it, and bleſſing on the <hi>Parliaments</hi> proceedings in it, that men which ſhal oppoſe it, may wel be ſaid to fight againſt the very arm of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> and ſlight many a glorious work which God hath done by weak and ordinary <hi>instruments.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many men nouriſh their <hi>diſcontents</hi> againſt it, by the preſent diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers they finde in the <hi>Nation,</hi> and are apt to think, and be made beleeve, That our condition is worſe then it was in the time of the late King, by reaſon of Taxes and Oppreſſions; They ſhould conſider the cauſe may be in themſelves, who give no better ground of ſecurity to the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> of an honeſt and faithful compliance, but by their new <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:165455:10"/> keep up our fears, which makes them keep up an Army: and had they been wiſe men who thus object, they would have conſidered, that we are not onely framing a new <hi>Government,</hi> but changing the old, and that we are not in <hi>in Republica Platonis,</hi> but <hi>in face Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's eaſie to frame an <hi>Idea</hi> of a new <hi>Government,</hi> and as eaſie to live under it in peace, had we all one minde; but not ſo eaſie (without much coſt) to alter an old one, where ſo many parties are engaged and diſ-affected, and ſo much rubbiſh to be removed. Were we to begin the world again, and to chooſe for our ſelves, having hearts, we ſhould not need Swords, and then <hi>An AGREEMENT of the PEOPLE</hi> (though not according to the <hi>Levellers</hi> Anarchical model) might be a <hi>Foundation of PEACE;</hi> but as it is with us, Men muſt be awed with Swords, as children are with rods, until they have learnt Reaſon, and come to be ſenſible of their own good, and learn to diſtinguiſh between <hi>what is done for preſent neceſſity to prevent farther miſery, and what is done in times of Peace, by abſolute Prerogative and Tyranny. Me thinks to ſee what is done, and how hopeful affairs look, ſhould be enough to ſwallow up the preſent ſence of preſſures, and allay the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings of mens spirits, whereby theſe oppreſſions are like to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and made heavier;</hi> And though it cannot be denied but the keeping up of the Army is a burthen, yet, it is ſo neceſſary, That it's an abſolute preſervative againſt more intollerable oppreſſions, that would not only <hi>burthen us, but utterly undoe us.</hi> And if we all expect eaſe, let us contribute to the procuring of it; if it ſeem hard by our purſes, let us go a neerer, and cheaper way by our compliances, and the intire union of our hearts and affections in theſe waies which are lawful and neceſſary, for were it not for our <hi>Claſſical diſcontents,</hi> and ſecret diſlikes which we nouriſh againſt perſons, and things, all theſe <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions</hi> would ſoon be removed; and we may well bear a little of the trouble, who are cauſes or inſtruments to create it; And truly for us who have had ſuch experiences of the ſad and doleful effects of <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> it were almoſt worth the hazarding the peace of one Generation, but to make an experiment of another <hi>Government,</hi> and ſpend our time in War (if it muſt be ſo) to procure peace for our Poſterity, as our Anceſtors have done in ſlavery, but to keep theirs.</p>
            <p>I can only wiſh, That all honeſt men would reflect on their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and what a perfect <hi>Dilemma</hi> is upon them, which cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165455:11"/> that either they muſt eſpouſe the old quarrel they firſt fought againſt, and incorporate with that Generation of <hi>Malignants</hi> which we have profeſt againſt, and God hath appeared againſt, and ſo reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their loſt hopes, or elſe joyn in with the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Army in this preſent <hi>Government,</hi> and diligently proſecute the remainders of Peace and <hi>Liberty,</hi> which we are in ſo promiſing a way to obtain. How much better is it to joyn in with our friends, though they have acted a little faſter, or ſomewhat beyond our model (ſeeing a ſurer foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is laid, though it be ſomewhat deep) then to give encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our common enemy to deſtroy both themſelves and us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and if we cannot meet in every line of the Circumference, yet, it's ſafe to meet in the Centre.</p>
            <p>I can but ſpeak for my ſelf, <hi>Quem fugiam ſcio, I know whom to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void:</hi> Two ſorts of men which are the utmoſt <hi>extremes, The old Malignants, and the new Levellers;</hi> This laſt was begotten in the ſame womb, only there was a mixture of ſeeds in the conception, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned as a reſerve to effect that which malignancy could not do; they both have one end, the deſtruction of this Government, though the pretences and ways of acting it are different; we have yet ſayled ſafe between theſe two rocks, and may (if we have hearts) prevent the miſchiefes of both, and ſee Liberty exactly ſtated, and juſtly reſtrained with the Golden reynes of Juſtice, Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and limited by Religion and Conſcience, and Juſtice ſitting on the Throne, poyſed with Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, whoſe freſh and Criſtal ſtreams ſhall glyde ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and inſenſibly, yea, run by every mans dore to refreſh all his injoyments. Wheras while we grate on the diſtempers of the times, and repine at former actings through inconſideration of our preſent opportunity, and ignorance of the deſigns that are upon us under ſpecious pretences, not making im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of what is before us, we ſhall ere we are aware, either be reduced back to Prerogative Tyranny, and be a thouſand times in worſe bondage then we were, or run into Levelling Confuſion; The Parliament and Army have done their endeavor, if men wil be miſerable, and ſuffer themſelves to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, they muſt blame none but themſelves, if they be miſerable. God will go on with his work, and finiſh it in righteouſneſs, and will prepare hiding places for thoſe which have faithfully oppoſed the common Enemies of Religion and Liberty, while theſe men, who to pleaſe their own diſcontents, or to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie Malignant inſtruments, are contented to ſell away their birth right for a meſs of pottage, and ſacrifice their dear bought advantages on their own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            <p>I would onely add this as my prayer and deſire for any honeſt, zealous, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hearts, That they may never feel that miſery, which, by their diſtance and ſecret differences, they may bring on this Nation, which is in ſo fair and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a condition of enjoying that happineſs, which all the Kingdoms, round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, will envy us for, if our own unreaſonable diſtempers do not hinder.</p>
            <closer>—Et ſic liberavi animam meam.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
